Finding Aid for Arthur R. Kooker papers, 1850-1882
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Arthur R. Kooker papers 1850-1882
Kooker, Arthur R. (Arthur Raymond), 1907-1978, collector.
0.5 linear feet and 1 oversize folder
85247 Aa 2; Ac
Arthur R. Kooker was a professor of history at the University of Southern California. His specialty was the anti-slavery movement. In the course of his work on his dissertation, Kooker acquired, from different sources, material pertaining to the anti-slavery movement in Michigan. Collection includes correspondence, notebooks, writings, and genealogical material of Nathan M. Thomas, Schoolcraft, Michigan, physician, anti-slavery spokesman and activist, agent for Signal of Liberty (abolitionist newspaper) and conductor on the underground railroad; include letter describing Kansas in 1856, letters discussing pre- and post-Civil War politics, especially as relates to anti-slavery, and letters from Gerrit Smith, 1858-1859.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Arthur Kooker and his wife (donor no. 1487 ) and came to the library in two accessions, 1979 and 1984
No further additions to the papers expected.
The collection is open to research.
Arthur R. Kooker was a professor of history at the University of Southern California. His specialty was the anti-slavery movement. In the course of his work on his dissertation, Kooker acquired from different sources pertaining to the anti-slavery movement in Michigan.
The Arthur R. Kooker collection consists of collected materials on the anti-slavery movement in Michigan. It came to the library in two principal accessions, 1979 and 1984. The collection is small but rich in source material. Included are correspondence, notebooks, writings, and genealogical material of Nathan M. Thomas, who was a Schoolcraft, Michigan physician and anti-slavery activist. Thomas was agent for the abolitionist newspaper, The Signal of Liberty, and a conductor on the underground railroad. The collection includes letters discussing pre- and post-Civil War politics, especially relating to the issue of slavery. Of special note is a letter describing the situation in Kansas in 1856 and letters from Gerrit Smith, 1858-185. One of Kooker's interest was the underground railroad. Among the materials that he collected is a notebook probably compiled by a conductor in which he lists the stops of safe haven in the journey from the South through Michigan and into Canada. This volume also lists the names of fugitive slaves who made their way to Canada.
Subjects:
Kansas.; Schoolcraft (Mich.).; Antislavery movements--Michigan.; Underground Railroad--Michigan.; United States--Politics and government--1845-1861.; United States--Politics and government--1861-1865.; United States--Politics and government--1865-1877.; Thomas, Nathan M. (Nathan Macy), 1803-1887.; Smith, Gerrit, 1797-1874.
- Collected papers
  - Correspondence (Box 1)
    - Undated, 1829 and 1850-1854 (Box 1)
    - 1855-1860 (Box 1)
      (include letters of Gerrit Smith, 1858-1859)
    - 1861-1868, 1872, 1874 (Box 1)
  - Autobiographical essays, 1868 and undated (Box 1)
  - Genealogical material (Box 1)
  - Letter detailing operation of the underground railroad, 1882 (Box 1)
  - Paper regarding an Ann Arbor Michigan home that was a station along the underground railroad (Box 1)
  - Paper regarding Laura Smith Haviland (Box 1)
  - Research notes and miscellanea (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous and fragmentary, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Notebooks and journals, 5 volumes (Box 1)
  - Anti-slavery newspapers
    - National Enquirer and Constitutional Advocate of Universal Liberty (Philadelphia, Pa.), 1837 (Folder 1)
    - The Northern Independent (Auburn, N.Y.), 1857 (Folder 1)
    - The Pennsylvania Freeman (Philadelphia, Pa.), 1838-1840 (Folder 1)
    - The Philanthropist (Cincinnati, Ohio), 1837-1839 (Folder 1)
    - The Portage County Democrat (Ravenna, Ohio), 1859 (Folder 1)
    - Broadside, "The Perils of Freedom in Kansas! The Crisis at Hand!! Speech of Gov. Reeder," 1856 (Folder 1)